<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Tafsir Sains </string>
    <string name="intro">Introduction</string>
    <string name="intro_detail">Ever since the dawn of human life on this planet, Man has always tried to understand Nature, his own place in the scheme of Creation and the purpose of Life itself. In this quest for Truth, spanning many centuries and diverse civilizations, organized religion has shaped human life and, to a large extent, has determined the cour se of history. While some religions have been based on written text, claimed by their followers to be divinely inspired, others have relied solely on human experience.\n"
                    "Al-Qur’an, the main source of  the Islamic faith, is  a book believed by its follower s, the Muslims, to be completely of Divine origin. Muslims also believe that it contains guidance for all humankind. Since the message of the Qur’an is believed to be for all times, it should be relevant to every age. But does the Qur’an pass this test?\n"
                    "In this booklet, I intend to give an objective analysis of the Muslim belief regarding the Divine origin of the Qur’an, particularly in the light of established scientific discoveries.\n"
                    "There was a time, in the history of world civilization, when ‘miracles’, or what were perceived to be miracles, took precedence over human reason and logic. Of cour se, the normal defination of ‘miracle’ is simply, anything that takes place out of the normal course of life and for which humankind has no explanation.\n"
                    "However, we must be careful before accepting something as a miracle. In 1993, ‘The Times of India’, Mumbai, reported that ‘a saint’ by the name ‘Baba Pilot’ claimed to have stayed continuously submerged under water in  a tank for three consecutive days and nights. However, when reporters wanted to examine the bottom of the tank  of water in which he claimed to have performed his ‘miraculous feat’, he refused to let them do so. He argued by asking as to how one could examine the womb of a mother that gives birth to a child. Obviously the ‘saint’ had something to conceal! His claim was a gimmick simply to gain publicity.\n"
                    "Surely, no modern person with even the slightest inkling towards rational thinking would accept  such a ‘miracle’. If such false miracles are the tests of divinity, then we would have to accept all world famous magicians known for their ingenious magical tricks and illusions, as genuine God-men!\n"
                    "A book, claiming to be of Divine origin, is in effect, claiming to be a miracle. Such a claim should be easily verifiable in any age, according to the standards of that age. Muslims believe, that the Qur’an is the last and final revelation of God, the miracle of miracles, revealed as a mercy to mankind. Let us therefore investigate the veracity of this belief.\n"
                    " \n"
                    "THE CHALLENGE OF THE QUR’AN\n"
                    "Literature and poetry have been instruments of human expression and creativity, in all cultures. The world also witnessed an age when li terature and poetry occupied pride of position, similar to that now enjoyed by science and technology.\n"
                    "Even non-Muslim scholars agree that the Qur’an is Arabic literature par excellence – that it is the best Arabic literature on the face of the earth. The Qur’an challenges mankind to produce the likes of it:\n"
                    "وَإِنْ كُنْتُمْ فِي رَيْبٍ مِمَّا نَزَّلْنَا عَلَىٰ عَبْدِنَا فَأْتُوا بِسُورَةٍ مِنْ مِثْلِهِ وَادْعُوا شُهَدَاءَكُمْ مِنْ دُونِ اللَّهِ إِنْ كُنْتُمْ صَادِقِينَ\n"
                    "\" And if you are in doubt as to what we have revealed from time to time to Our servant, then produce a Surah like thereunto; And call your witnesses or helpers (if there are any) besides Allah, if your (doubts) are true. But if you cannot and of a surety you cannot then fear the Fire whose fuel is Men and Stones which is prepared for those who reject faith\" [ 2:23-24 ]\n"
                    "The challenge of the Qur’an, is to produce a single Surah (chapter) like the Surahs it contains. The same challenge is repeated in the Qur’an  several  times. The challenge to produce a Surah , which, in beauty, eloquence, depth and meaning is at least somewhat similar to a Qur’anic Surah remains unmet to this day.\n"
                    "A modern rational man, however, would  never  accept a religious scripture which says, in the best possible poetic language, that the world is flat. This is because we live in an age, where human reason, logic and science are given primacy. Not many would accept the Qur’an’s extraordinarily beautiful language, as proof of its Divine origin. Any scripture claiming to be a divine revelation must also be acceptable on the strength of its own reason and logic.\n"
                    "According to the famous physicist and Nobel Prize winner, Albert Einstein, “Science without religion is lame. Religion without science is blind.” Let us therefore study the Qur’an, and analyze whether the Qur’an and Modern Science are compatible or incompatible?\n"
                    "The Qur’an is not a book of Science but a book of ‘Signs’, i.e. Aayaats . There are more than six thousand ‘Signs’ in the Qur’an of which more than a thousand deal with hard core Science.\n"
                    "We all know that many a times Science takes a ‘U-turn’. In this book I have considered only established scientific facts and not hypotheses and theories based on mere assumptions and not backed by proof."</string>
    <string name="astro">Astronomy</string>
    <string name="astro_detail">"CREATION OF THE UNIVERSE: ‘THE BIG BANG’\n"
                    "The creation of the universe is explained by astrophysicists as a widely accepted phenomenon, popularly known as ‘The Big Bang’. It is supported by observational and experimental data gathered by astronomers\tand\tastrophysicists  for\tdecades. According to ‘The Big Bang’, the whole universe was initially one big mass (Primary Nebula). Then there was a ‘Big Bang’ (Secondary Separation) which resulted in the formation of Galaxies. These then divided to form stars, planets, the sun, the moon, etc. The origin of the universe was unique and the probability of it happening by ‘chance’ is nil.\n"
                    "The Qur’an contains the following verse regarding the origin of the universe:\n"
                    "أَوَلَمْ يَرَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا أَنَّ السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضَ كَانَتَا رَتْقًا فَفَتَقْنَاهُمَا ۖ\n"
                    "\" Do not the unbelievers see that the heavens and the earth were joined together (as one unit of Creation), before we clove them asunder\" [ 21:30 ] \n"
                    "The striking similarity between the Qur’anic verse and ‘The Big Bang’ is inescapable! How could a book, which first appeared in the deserts of Arabia 1400 years ago, contain this profoun d scientific truth?\n"
                    " \n"
                    "INITIAL GASEOUS MASS BEFORE CREATION OF GALAXIES\n"
                    "Scientists agree that before the galaxies in the universe were formed, celestial matter was initially in the form of gaseous matter. In short, huge gaseous matter or clouds were present before the formation of the galaxies. To describe initial celestial matter, the word ‘smoke’ is more appropriate than gas. The following Qur’anic verse refers to this state of the universe by the word dukhaan which means smoke.\n"
                    "ثُمَّ اسْتَوَىٰ إِلَى السَّمَاءِ وَهِيَ دُخَانٌ فَقَالَ لَهَا وَلِلْأَرْضِ ائْتِيَا طَوْعًا أَوْ كَرْهًا قَالَتَا أَتَيْنَا طَائِعِينَ\n"
                    "\" Moreover, He Comprehended in His design the sky, and it had been (as) smoke: He said to it and to the eartj: Come ye togehter, willingly or unwillingly. They said: we do come (together) in willing obedience\" [ 41:11 ]\n"
                    "Again, this fact is a corollary to the ‘Big Bang’ and was not known to anyone before the prophetehood of Muhammad (Peace be upon him) 1. What then, could have been the source of this knowledge?\n"
                    "SHAPE OF THE EARTH IS SPHERICAL\n"
                    "In early times, people believed that the earth was flat. For centuries, men were afraid to venture out too far, for fear of falling off the edge! Sir Francis Drake was the fir s t person who proved that the earth is spherical when he sailed around it in 1597.\n"
                    "Consider the following Qur’anic verse regarding the alternation of day and night:\n"
                    "أَلَمْ تَرَ أَنَّ اللَّهَ يُولِجُ اللَّيْلَ فِي النَّهَارِ وَيُولِجُ النَّهَارَ فِي اللَّيْلِ\n"
                    "\" Seest thou not that Allahh merges Night into Day and He merges Day to Night ?\" [ 32:29 ]\n"
                    "Merging here means that the night slowly and gradually changes to day and vice versa. This phenomenon can only take place if the earth is spherical. If the earth was flat, there would have been a sudden change from night to day and from day to night.\n"
                    "The following verse also alludes to the spherical shape of the earth:\n"
                    "خَلَقَ السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضَ بِالْحَقِّ ۖ يُكَوِّرُ اللَّيْلَ عَلَى النَّهَارِ وَيُكَوِّرُ النَّهَارَ عَلَى اللَّيْلِ\n"
                    "\"He created the heavens and the earth in true (prepositions): He makes the Night overlap the Day, and the Day overlap the Night\" [ 39:5 ]\n"
                    "The Arabic word used here is Kawwara meaning ‘to overlap’ or ‘to coil’– the way a turban is wound around the head. The overlapping or coiling of the day and night can only take place if the earth is spherical.\n"
                    "The earth is not exactly round like a ball, but geo-spherical, i.e. i t is flattened at the poles. The following verse contain s a description of the earth’s shape:\n"
                    "وَالْأَرْضَ بَعْدَ ذَٰلِكَ دَحَاهَا\n"
                    "\"And the Earth, moreover hath He made eggshaped\" [ 79:30 ]\n"
                    "The Arabic word for egg here is dahaahaa 1 which means an ostrich-egg. The shape of an ostrich-egg resembles the geo-sp herical shape of the earth.\n"
                    "Thus the Qur’an correctly describes the shape of the earth, though the prevalent notion when the Qur’an was revealed was that the earth was flat.\n"
                    "\n"
                    "MOONLIGHT IS REFLECTED LIGHT\n"
                    "It was believed by earlier civilizations that the moon emanates its own light. Science now tells us that the light of the moon is reflected light. However this fact was mentioned in the Qur’an 1,400 years ago in the following verse:\n"
                    "تَبَارَكَ الَّذِي جَعَلَ فِي السَّمَاءِ بُرُوجًا وَجَعَلَ فِيهَا سِرَاجًا وَقَمَرًا مُنِيرًا\n"
                    "\" Blessed is He Who made Constellations in the skies, and placed therein a Lamp and a Moon giving Light\" [ 25:61 ]\n"
                    "The Arabic word for the sun in the Qur’an, is shams. It is also referred to as siraaj which means a ‘torch’ or as wahhaaj meaning ‘a blazing lamp’ or as diya which means ‘shining glory’. All three descriptions are appropriate to the sun, since i t generates intense heat and light by its internal combustion. The Arabic word for the  moon  is  qam ar  and  i t is described in the Qur’an as m uneer which is a body that gives noor i.e. reflected light. Again, the Qur’anic description matches perfectly with the true nature of the moon which does not give off light by itself and is an inactive body that  reflects  the light of the sun. Not once in the Qur’an, is the moon mentioned as siraaj, wahhaaj or diya nor the sun as noor or m uneer . This implies that the Qur’an recognizes the difference between the nature of sunlight and moonlight.\n"
                    "The following verses relate to the nature of light from the sun and the moon:\n"
                    "هُوَ الَّذِي جَعَلَ الشَّمْسَ ضِيَاءً وَالْقَمَرَ نُورًا\n"
                    "\" It is He who made the sun to be a shining glory and the moon to be a light (of beauty)\" [ 10:5 ]\n"
                    "أَلَمْ تَرَوْا كَيْفَ خَلَقَ اللَّهُ سَبْعَ سَمَاوَاتٍ طِبَاقًا; وَجَعَلَ الْقَمَرَ فِيهِنَّ نُورًا وَجَعَلَ الشَّمْسَ سِرَاجًا\n"
                    "\" See ye not how Allah has created the seven heavens one above another; And made the moon a light in their midst, and made the sun as a (Gloroius) Lamp?\" [ 71:15-16 ]\n"
                    "The Glorious Quran and modern science, are thus in perfect agreement about the differences in the nature of sunlight and moonlight.\n"
                    "THE SUN ROTATES\n"
                    "For a long time European philosophers and scientists believed that the earth stood still in the centre of the universe and every other body including the sun moved around it. In the West, this geocentric concept of the universe was prevalent right from the time of Ptolemy in the second century B.C. In 1512, Nicholas Copernicus put forward his Heliocentric Theory of Planetary Motion, which asserted that the sun is\n"
                    " \n"
                    "motionless at the centre of the solar system with the planets revolving around it.\n"
                    "In 1609, the German scientist Yohannus Keppler published the ‘ Astronomia Nova ’. In this he concluded that not only do the planets move in elliptical orbits around the sun, they also rotate upon their axes at irregular speeds. With this knowledge it became possible for European scientists to explain correctly many of the mechanisms of the solar system, including the sequence of night and day.\n"
                    "After these discoveries, it was thought that the Sun was stationary and did not rotate about its axis like the Earth. I remember having studied this fallacy from Geography books during my school days.\n"
                    "Consider the following Qur’anic verse:\n"
                    "وَهُوَ الَّذِي خَلَقَ اللَّيْلَ وَالنَّهَارَ وَالشَّمْسَ وَالْقَمَرَ ۖ كُلٌّ فِي فَلَكٍ يَسْبَحُونَ\n"
                    "\"it is he Who created the Night and the Day, and the Sun and the Moon: All (the celestial bodies) swim along, each inits rounded course.\" [ 21:33 ]\n"
                    "The Arabic word used in  the above verse is yasbahoon . This word is derived from the word sabaha . I t carries with i t the idea of motion that comes from any moving body. If you use this word for a person on the ground, it would not  mean that he is rolling but would imply that he is walking or\n"
                    " \n"
                    "running. If you use this word for  a  person in water, i t would not mean that he is floating but would imply that he is swimming.\n"
                    "Similarly, if you use the word yasbah for a celestial body such as the sun, it would not only mean that it is flying through space but would also mean  that it is rotating as i t goes through space. Most school textbooks have now incorporated the fact that the sun rotates about its axis. The rotation of the sun about its own axis can be proved with the help of an equipment that project s the image of the sun on the top of a table, so that one can examine the image of the sun without being blinded. It is noticed that the sun has spots which complete a circular motion once every 25 days i.e. the sun takes approximately 25 days to rotate round its axis.\n"
                    "The sun travels through space at roughly 240 km per second, and takes about 200 million years to complete one revolution around the centre of our Milky Way Galaxy\n"
                    "لَا الشَّمْسُ يَنْبَغِي لَهَا أَنْ تُدْرِكَ الْقَمَرَ وَلَا اللَّيْلُ سَابِقُ النَّهَارِ ۚ وَكُلٌّ فِي فَلَكٍ يَسْبَحُونَ\n"
                    "\"it is not permitted to the sun to catch up the moon, norcan the Night out strip the Day: Each (just) swims along in (its own) orbit (according to Law)\" [ 36:40 ]\n"
                    "This verse mentions an essential fact discovered\n"
                    " \n"
                    "only   recently  by   modern\tastronomy, i.e. the existence of the individual orbits of the Sun and the Moon, and their journey through space with their own motion.\n"
                    "The ‘fixed place’ towards which the sun travels, carrying with it the solar system, has been located preirsely by modern astronomy. It has been given a name, the Solar Apex. The solar system is indeed moving in space towards a point situated in the con stellation of Hercules (alpha Lyrae) whose exact location is now firmly established.\n"
                    "The moon rotates around i t s axis in the same duration  that it  takes to revolve  around the earth. I t takes approximately 29½ days to complete one rotation.\n"
                    "One cannot help but be amazed at the scientific accuracy of the Qur’anic verses. Should we not ponder over the question: “What is the source of knowledge contained in the Qur’an?”\n"
                    "THE SUN WILL EXTINGUISH\n"
                    "The light of the sun is due to a chemical process on its surface that has been taking place continuou sly for the past five billion years. It will come to an end at some point of time in the future, when the sun will be totally extinguished, leading to extinction of all life on earth. Regarding the impermanence of the sun’s existence, the Qur’an says:\n"
                    "وَالشَّمْسُ تَجْرِي لِمُسْتَقَرٍّ لَهَا ۚ ذَٰلِكَ تَقْدِيرُ الْعَزِيزِ الْعَلِيمِ\n"
                    "\"And the Sun runs its course for a period determined for it; that is the decree of (Him) the exalted in Might, the All-Knowing\" [ 36:38 ]\n"
                    "The Arabic word used here is mustaqarr , which means a place or time that is determined. Thus the Qur’an says that the sun runs towards a determined place, and will do so only up to a pre-determined period of t ime – meaning that i t will end or extinguish.\n"
                    "\n"
                    "INTERSTELLAR MATTER\n"
                    "Space outside organized astronomical systems was earlier assumed to be a vacuum. Astrophysicists later discovered the presence of bridges of matter in this interstellar space. These bridges of matter are called plasma, and con sist of com pletely ionized gas containing equal number of free electrons and positive ions. Plasma is sometimes called the fourth state of matter (besides the three known  states viz. solid, liquid and gas). The Qur’an refers  to the presence of this interstellar material in the following verse:\n"
                    "الَّذِي خَلَقَ السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضَ وَمَا بَيْنَهُمَا\n"
                    "\"he Who created the heavens and the earth and all that is between\" [ 25:59 ]\n"
                    "It would be ridiculous for anyone to even suggest that the presence of interstellar galactic material was known 1400 years ago!\n"
                    "THE EXPANDING UNIVERSE\n"
                    "In 1925, American astronomer Edwin Hubble, provided observational evidence that all galaxies are moving away from one another, which implies that the universe is expanding. The expansion of the universe is now an established scientific fact. This is what the Qur’an says regarding the nature of the universe:\n"
                    "وَالسَّمَاءَ بَنَيْنَاهَا بِأَيْدٍ وَإِنَّا لَمُوسِعُونَ\n"
                    "\"With power and skill did We construct the Firmament: For it is We Who create the vastness of Space\" [ 51:57 ]\n"
                    "The Arabic word musioon is correctly translated as ‘expanding i t’, and i t refers to the creation of the expanding vastness of the universe.\n"
                    "One of the greatest astrophysicist Stephen Hawking, in his book, ‘A Brief History of Time’,\n"
                    " \n"
                    "says, “The discovery that the universe is expanding was one of the great intellectual revolutions of the 20th century.” The Qur’an mentioned the expansion of the universe, before man even learnt to build a telescope!\n"
                    "Some may say that the presence of astronomical facts in the Qur’an is not surprising since the Arabs were advanced in the field of astronomy. They are correct in acknowledging the advancement of the Arabs in the field of astronomy. However they fail to realize that the Qur’an was revealed centuries before the Arabs excelled in astronomy. Moreover many of the scientific facts mentioned above, such as the origin of the universe with a Big Bang, were not known to the Arabs even at the peak of their scientific\tadvancement.\tThe\tscientific\tfacts mentioned in the Qur’an are therefore not due to the Arabs’ advancement in astronomy. Indeed, the reverse is true: they advanced in  astronomy, because astronomy occu pies a place in the Qur’an.\n"</string>
    <string name="fisika">Physics</string>
    <string name="fisika_detail">ATOMS CAN BE DIVIDED
    In ancient times a well-known  theory by  the name of ‘Theory of Atomism’ was widely accepted. This theory was originally proposed by the Greeks, in particular by a scholar called Democritu s, who lived about 23 centuries ago. Democritus and the people that came after him, assumed that  the smallest unit of matter was the atom. The ancient Arabs used to believe the same. The Arabic word zarrah most commonly meant an atom. In recent times modern science has discovered that i t is possible to split even  an  atom. That  the atom can be  split further is a development of the 20 th century. Fourteen centuries ago this concept would have appeared unusual even to an Arab. For him the zarrah  was the limit beyond which one could not go. The following Qur’anic verse however, refuses to acknowledge this limit:
    وَقَالَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا لَا تَأْتِينَا السَّاعَةُ ۖ قُلْ بَلَىٰ وَرَبِّي لَتَأْتِيَنَّكُمْ عَالِمِ الْغَيْبِ ۖ لَا يَعْزُبُ عَنْهُ مِثْقَالُ ذَرَّةٍ فِي السَّمَاوَاتِ وَلَا فِي الْأَرْضِ وَلَا أَصْغَرُ مِنْ ذَٰلِكَ وَلَا أَكْبَرُ إِلَّا فِي كِتَابٍ مُبِينٍ
    The Unbelievers say, ‘Never to us will come The Hour’: say, ‘Nay! but most surely, by my Lord, it will come upon you by Him Who knows the unseen – from Whom is not hidden the least little atom in the Heavens or on earth: nor is there anything less than that, or greater, but is in the Record Perspicuous [Al Quran 34:3].
    This verse also refers to the Omniscience of God, His knowledge of all things, hidden or apparent. It then goes further and says that God is aware of everything, including what is smaller or bigger than the atom. Thus the verse clearly shows that i t is possible for something smaller than the atom to exist, a fact discovered only recently by modern science.
    </string>
    <string name="hidro">Hydrology</string>
    <string name="hidro_detail">THE WATER CYCLE
In 1580, Bernard Palissy was the fir s t person to describe the present day concept of ‘water cycle’. He described how water evaporates from the oceans and cools to form clouds. The clouds move inland where they r ise, condense and fall as rain. This water gathers as lakes and streams and flows back  to the ocean in a continuous cycle. In the 7th century B.C., Thales of Miletus believed that  surface spray of the ocean s was picked up by the wind and carried inland to fall as rain.
In earlier  times people did	not know the source of underground water. They thought the water of the oceans, under the effect of winds, was thrust towards the interior of the continents. They also believed that the water returned by a secret passage or the Great Abyss. This passage is connected to the ocean s and has been called the ‘Tartarus’, since Plato’s t ime. Even Descartes, a great thinker of the eighteenth century, subscribed to this view. Till the nineteenth century, Aristotle’s theory was s till  prevalent. According to this theory, water was condensed in cool mountain caverns and formed underground lakes that fed springs. Today, we have come to know that the rainwater that seeps into the cracks of the ground is responsible for this.
This is described by the Qur’an in the following verses:
        أَلَمْ تَرَ أَنَّ اللَّهَ أَنْزَلَ مِنَ السَّمَاءِ مَاءً فَسَلَكَهُ يَنَابِيعَ فِي الْأَرْضِ ثُمَّ يُخْرِجُ بِهِ زَرْعًا مُخْتَلِفًا أَلْوَانُهُ[Alquran 39:21]
        Seest thou not that Allah sends down rain from the sky, and leads it through springs in the earth? then He causes to grow, therewith, produce of various colours
        وَيُنَزِّلُ مِنَ السَّمَاءِ مَاءً فَيُحْيِي بِهِ الْأَرْضَ بَعْدَ مَوْتِهَا ۚ إِنَّ فِي ذَٰلِكَ لَآيَاتٍ لِقَوْمٍ يَعْقِلُونَ[Alquran 30:24]
        He sends down rain from the sky and with it gives life to the earth after it is dead: Verily in that are Signs for those who are wise
        وَأَنْزَلْنَا مِنَ السَّمَاءِ مَاءً بِقَدَرٍ فَأَسْكَنَّاهُ فِي الْأَرْضِ ۖ وَإِنَّا عَلَىٰ ذَهَابٍ بِهِ لَقَادِرُونَ[Alquran 23:18]
        “And We send down water from the sky according to (due) measure, and We cause it to soak in the soil; and We certainly are able to drain it off (with ease).”
        No other text dating back 1400 years ago gives such an accurate description of the water cycle.
        EVAPORATION
        وَالسَّمَاءِ ذَاتِ الرَّجْعِ[Alquran 86:11]
        “By the Firmament which returns (in its round),”
        WINDS IMPREGNATE CLOUDS
        وَأَرْسَلْنَا الرِّيَاحَ لَوَاقِحَ فَأَنْزَلْنَا مِنَ السَّمَاءِ مَاءً فَأَسْقَيْنَاكُمُوهُ[Alquran 15:22]
        “And We send the fecundating winds, then cause the rain to descend from the sky, therewith providing you with water (in abundance).”
        The Arabic word used here is lawaaqih which is the plural of laqih  from  laqaha ,  which  means to impregnate or fecundate. In this context, impregnate means that the wind pushes the clouds together increasing the condensation that causes lightning and thus rain. A similar description is foun d in the following verses of the Qur’an:
        أَلَمْ تَرَ أَنَّ اللَّهَ يُزْجِي سَحَابًا ثُمَّ يُؤَلِّفُ بَيْنَهُ ثُمَّ يَجْعَلُهُ رُكَامًا فَتَرَى الْوَدْقَ يَخْرُجُ مِنْ خِلَالِهِ وَيُنَزِّلُ مِنَ السَّمَاءِ مِنْ جِبَالٍ فِيهَا مِنْ بَرَدٍ فَيُصِيبُ بِهِ مَنْ يَشَاءُ وَيَصْرِفُهُ عَنْ مَنْ يَشَاءُ ۖ يَكَادُ سَنَا بَرْقِهِ يَذْهَبُ بِالْأَبْصَارِ[Alquran 24:43]
        "Seest thou not that Allah makes the clouds move gently, then joins them together, then makes them into a heap?–then wilt thou see rain issue forth from their midst. And He sends down from the sky mountain masses (of clouds) wherein is hail: He strikes therewith whom He pleases and He turns it away from whom He pleases. the vivid flash of His lightning well-nigh blinds the sight.”
        اللَّهُ الَّذِي يُرْسِلُ الرِّيَاحَ فَتُثِيرُ سَحَابًا فَيَبْسُطُهُ فِي السَّمَاءِ كَيْفَ يَشَاءُ وَيَجْعَلُهُ كِسَفًا فَتَرَى الْوَدْقَ يَخْرُجُ مِنْ خِلَالِهِ ۖ فَإِذَا أَصَابَ بِهِ مَنْ يَشَاءُ مِنْ عِبَادِهِ إِذَا هُمْ يَسْتَبْشِرُونَ[Alquran 30:48]
        “It is Allah Who sends the Winds, and they raise the Clouds: then does He spread them in the sky as He wills, and break them into fragments, until thou seest raindrops issue from the midst thereof: then when He has made them reach such of His servants as He wills, behold, they do rejoice!”
        Modern data on Hydrology agrees perfectly with the Quranic description on the same subject. The water cycle is described in several other verses of the Glorious Qur’an, including 7:57, 13:17, 25:48- 49, 35:9, 36:34, 45:5, 50:9-11, 56:68-70 and 67:30.
    </string>
    <string name="geologi">Geology</string>
    <string name="geo_detail">MOUNTAINS ARE LIKE TENT PEGS
In geology, the phenomenon of ‘folding’, is a recently discovered fact. Folding is responsible for the formation of mountain ranges. The earth’s crust, on which we live, is like a solid shell, while the deeper layers are hot and fluid, and thus inhospitable to any form of life. I t is also known  that  the stability of the mountains is linked to the phenomenon of folding, for i t was the folds that were to provide foundations for the reliefs that constitute the mountains.
Geologists tell us that the radius of the Earth is about 6,035 km and the crust on which we live is very thin, ranging between 2 to 35 km. Since the crust is thin, i t has a high possibility of shaking. Mountains act like stakes or tent pegs that hold the earth’s crust and give i t stability. The Qur’an contain s exactly such a description
        أَلَمْ نَجْعَلِ الْأَرْضَ مِهَادًا 0 وَالْجِبَالَ أَوْتَادًا [Alquran 78:6-7]
        “Have We not made the earth as a wide expanse, and the mountains as pegs?”
        The word awtaad means stakes or pegs  (like those used to anchor a tent); they are the  deep foun dations of geological folds. A book entitled ‘Earth’ is regarded as a basic reference textbook on geology in many universities around the world. One of the authors of this book is Dr. Frank Press, who was the President of the Academy of Sciences in the USA for 12 years and was the Science Advisor  to former  US  President J immy Carter. In this book, he illu strates the mountain in a wedge-shape and the mountain itself as a small part of the whole, whose root is deeply entrenched in the ground. 1 Accor ding to Dr. Press, the mountains play an important role in stabilizing the crust of the earth. The Qur’an clearly mentions the function of the mountains in preventing the earth from shaking:
        وَجَعَلْنَا فِي الْأَرْضِ رَوَاسِيَ أَنْ تَمِيدَ بِهِمْ [Alquran 21:31]
        “And We have set on the earth   mountains standing firm, lest it should shake with them.”
        The Qur’anic descriptions are in perfect agreement with modern geological data.
        MOUNTAINS FIRMLY FIXED
        The surface of the earth is broken into many rigid plates that are about 100 km in thickness. These plates float on a partially molten region called aesthenosphere.
Mountain formations occur at the boundary of the plates. The earth’s crust is 5 km thick below ocean s, about 35 km thick below flat continental surfaces and almost 80 km thick below great mountain ranges. These are the strong foundations on which mountains stand. The Qur’an refers to the strong mountain foun dations in the following verse:
وَالْجِبَالَ أَرْسَاهَا [Alquran 79:32]
      “And the mountains hath He firmly fixed.”
        Thus, the information contained in the Glorious Quran about the nature of mountains, is in perfect agreement with recent discoveries in geology.
    </string>
    <string name="ocean">Oceanology</string>
    <string name="ocean_detail">BARRIER BETWEEN SWEET AND SALT WATERS
        مَرَجَ الْبَحْرَيْنِ يَلْتَقِيَانِ 0 بَيْنَهُمَا بَرْزَخٌ لَا يَبْغِيَانِ[Alquran 55:19-20]
        “He has let free the two bodies	  of flowing water, meeting together: Between them is a Barrier which they do not transgress.”
        In  the  Arabic  text  the  word  barzakh	means a barrier or a partition. This barrier, however, is not a physical partition. The Arabic word maraja literally means ‘they both meet and mix with each other’. Early commentators of the Qur’an were unable to explain the two opposite meanings for the two bodies of water, i.e. they meet and mix, and at the same time there is a barrier between them. Modern Science has discovered that in the places where two different seas meet, there is a barrier between them. This barrier divides the two seas so that each sea has its own temperature, salinity and density. 1 Oceanologists are now in a better position to explain this verse. There is a slanted unseen water barrier between the two seas through which water from one sea passes to the other.
But when the water from one sea enters the other sea, it loses its distinctive characteristic and
becomes homogenized with the other water. In a way this barrier serves as a transitional homogenizing area for the two waters.
This phenomenon is also mentioned in the following verse of the Quran:
        وَجَعَلَ بَيْنَ الْبَحْرَيْنِ حَاجِزًا ۗ [Alquran 27:61]
        “And made a separating bar between the two bodies of flowing water?”
        This phenomenon occurs in several places, including the divider between the Mediterranean and the Atlantic Ocean at Gibralter. A white bar can also be clearly seen at Cape Point, Cape Peninsula, South Africa where the Atlantic Ocean meets the Indian Ocean.
But when the Qur’an speaks about the divider between fresh and salt water, i t mentions the existence of “a forbidding partition” with the barrier
        وَهُوَ الَّذِي مَرَجَ الْبَحْرَيْنِ هَٰذَا عَذْبٌ فُرَاتٌ وَهَٰذَا مِلْحٌ أُجَاجٌ وَجَعَلَ بَيْنَهُمَا بَرْزَخًا وَحِجْرًا مَحْجُورًا [Alquran 25:53]
        “It is He Who has let free the two bodies of flowing water: one palatable and sweet, and the other salty and bitter yet has He made a barrier between them, and a partition that is forbidden to be passed."
        Modern science has discovered that in estuaries, where fresh (sweet) and salt water meet, the situation is somewhat different from that found in places where two salt water seas meet. It has been discovered that what distinguishes fresh water from salt water in estuaries is a “pycnocline zone with a marked density discontinuity separating the two layers.”1 This partition (zone of separation) has a salinity different from both the fresh water and the salt water.2
This phenomenon occurs in several places, including Egypt, where the river Nile flows into the Mediterranean Sea.
These scientific phenomena mentioned in the Qur’an was also confirmed by Dr. William Hay, a well- known marine scientist and Professor of Geological Sciences at the University of Colorado, U.S.A.

DARKNESS IN DEPTHS OF OCEAN
Prof. Durga Rao is a world renowned expert in the field of Marine Geology and was a professor at King Abdul Aziz University in Jeddah. He was asked to comment on the following verse:
أَوْ كَظُلُمَاتٍ فِي بَحْرٍ لُجِّيٍّ يَغْشَاهُ مَوْجٌ مِنْ فَوْقِهِ مَوْجٌ مِنْ فَوْقِهِ سَحَابٌ ۚ ظُلُمَاتٌ بَعْضُهَا فَوْقَ بَعْضٍ إِذَا أَخْرَجَ يَدَهُ لَمْ يَكَدْ يَرَاهَا ۗ وَمَنْ لَمْ يَجْعَلِ اللَّهُ لَهُ نُورًا فَمَا لَهُ مِنْ نُورٍ[40:Alquran 24]
        "Or (the Unbelievers’ state) is like the depths of darkness in a vast deep ocean, 1 Oceanography, Gross, p. 242. Also see Introductory Oceanography, Thurman, pp. 300-301. 2 Oceanography, Gross, p. 244 and Introductory Oceanography , Thurman, pp. 300-301. overwhelmed with billow topped by billow, topped by (dark) clouds: depths of darkness, one above another: if a man stretches out his hand, he can hardly see it! For any to whom Allah giveth not light, there is no light!”
        Prof. Rao said that scientists have only now been able to confirm, with the help of modern equipment, that there is darkness in the depths of the ocean. Humans are unable to dive unaided underwater for more than 20 to 30 metres, and cannot survive in the deep oceanic regions at a depth of more than 200 metres. This verse does not refer to all seas because not every sea can be described as having accumulated darkness layered one over another. It refers especially to a deep sea or deep ocean, as the Qur’an says, “darkness in a vast deep ocean”. This layered darkness in a deep ocean is the result of two causes:
1.	A light ray is composed of seven colours seen in the rainbow. These seven colours are Violet,

Indigo, Blue, Green, Yellow, Orange and Red (VIBGYOR). The light ray undergoes refraction when it hits water. The upper 10 to
15 metres of water absorb the red colour. Therefore, if a diver is 25 metres under water and gets wounded, he would not be able to see the red colour of his blood, because the red colour does not reach this depth. Similarly, orange rays are absorbed at 30 to 50 metres, yellow at 50 to 100 metres, green at 100 to 200 metres, and finally, blue beyond 200 metres and violet and indigo above 200 metres. Due to successive disappearance of colour, one layer after another, the ocean progressively becomes darker, i.e. darkness takes place in layers of light. Below a depth of 1000 meters there is com plete darkness. 1
2.	The sun’s rays are absorbed by clouds which in turn scatter light rays thus causing a layer of darkness under the clouds. This is the fir s t layer of darkness. When light rays reach the surface of the ocean they are reflected by the wave surface giving i t a shiny appearance. Therefore, it is the waves which reflect light and cause darkness. The unreflected light penetrates into the depths of the ocean. Thus, the	ocean	has	two	parts.	The	surface characterized by light and warmth and the depth characterized by darkness. The surface

is further separated from the deep part of the ocean by waves.
The internal waves cover the deep waters of seas and ocean s because the deep waters have a higher density than the waters above them.
The darkness begins below the internal waves. Even the fish in the depths of the ocean cannot see; their only source of light is from their own bodies.
The Qur’an describes this aptly:
“Darkness in a vast deep ocean overwhelmed with waves topped by waves”.
In other words, above these waves there are more types of waves, i.e. those found on the surface of the ocean. The Qur’anic verse continues, “topped by (dark) clouds; depths of darkness, one above another.”
These clouds as explained are barriers one over the other that further cause darkness by absorption of colour s at different levels.
Prof. Durga Rao concluded by saying, “1400 years ago a normal human being could not explain this phenomenon	in	so	much	detail.	Thus	the information must have come from a supernatural source”.
        is further separated from the deep part of the ocean by waves.
The internal waves cover the deep waters of seas and ocean s because the deep waters have a higher density than the waters above them.
The darkness begins below the internal waves. Even the fish in the depths of the ocean cannot see; their only source of light is from their own bodies.
The Qur’an describes this aptly:
“Darkness in a vast deep ocean overwhelmed with waves topped by waves”.
In other words, above these waves there are more types of waves, i.e. those found on the surface of the ocean. The Qur’anic verse continues, “topped by (dark) clouds; depths of darkness, one above another.”
These clouds as explained are barriers one over the other that further cause darkness by absorption of colour s at different levels.
Prof. Durga Rao concluded by saying, “1400 years ago a normal human being could not explain this phenomenon	in	so	much	detail.	Thus	the information must have come from a supernatural source”.
        وَهُوَ الَّذِي خَلَقَ مِنَ الْمَاءِ بَشَرًا فَجَعَلَهُ نَسَبًا وَصِهْرًا ۗ وَكَانَ رَبُّكَ قَدِيرًا[Alquran 25:54]
        “It is He Who has Created man from water: then has He established relationships of lineage and marriage:for thy Lord has power (over all things).”
        Was i t possible 14 centuries ago for any human being to guess that every living being was made from water? Moreover would such a guess be conceivable by a human being in the deserts of Arabia where there has always been scarcity of water?
    </string>
    <string name="botani">Botany</string>
    <string name="botani_detail">PLANTS HAVE MALE AND FEMALE
Previously, humans did not know that plants too have male and female gender distinctions. Botany states that every plant has a male and female gender. Even the plants that are unisexual have distinct elements of both male and female
        وَأَنْزَلَ مِنَ السَّمَاءِ مَاءً فَأَخْرَجْنَا بِهِ أَزْوَاجًا مِنْ نَبَاتٍ شَتَّىٰ[Alquran 20:53]
        “ ‘And has sent down water from the sky.’ With it have We produced diverse pairs of plants each separate from the others.”
        FRUITS HAVE MALE AND FEMALE
        وَمِنْ كُلِّ الثَّمَرَاتِ جَعَلَ فِيهَا زَوْجَيْنِ اثْنَيْنِ[Alquran 13:3]
        Fruit is the end product of reproduction of the superior plants. The stage preceding fruit is the flower, which has male and female organs (stamens and ovules). Once pollen has been carried to the flower, they bear fruit, which in turn matures and frees i t s seed. All fruits therefore imply the existence of male and female organs; a fact that is mentioned in the Qur’an.
        In certain species, fruit can come from non-fertilized flowers (parthenocarpic fruit) e.g. bananas, certain types of pineapple, fig, orange, vine, etc. They also have definite sexual characteristics.
        EVERYTHING MADE IN PAIRS
        وَمِنْ كُلِّ شَيْءٍ خَلَقْنَا زَوْجَيْنِ لَعَلَّكُمْ تَذَكَّرُونَ[Alquran 51:49]
        “And of everything We have created pairs.”
        This verse lays emphasis on everything. Besides humans, animals, plants and fruits, it may also be referring to electricity in which the atoms con sist of negatively – and positively – charged electrons and protons. And many more things!
        سُبْحَانَ الَّذِي خَلَقَ الْأَزْوَاجَ كُلَّهَا مِمَّا تُنْبِتُ الْأَرْضُ وَمِنْ أَنْفُسِهِمْ وَمِمَّا لَا يَعْلَمُونَ[Alquran 36:36]
        “Glory to Allah, Who created in pairs all things that the earth produces, as well as their own (human) kind and (other) things of which they have no knowledge.”
        The Qur’an here says that everything is created in pairs, including things that the humans do not know at present and may discover later
    </string>
    <string name="zologi">Zoologi</string>
    <string name="zologi_detail">ANIMALS AND BIRDS LIVE IN COMMUNITIES
        وَمَا مِنْ دَابَّةٍ فِي الْأَرْضِ وَلَا طَائِرٍ يَطِيرُ بِجَنَاحَيْهِ إِلَّا أُمَمٌ أَمْثَالُكُمْ ۚ م[Alquran 6:38]
        “There is not an animal (that lives) on the earth, nor a being that flies on its wings, but (forms part of) communities like you.”
        Research has shown that animals and birds live in communities, i.e. they organize, and live and work together.
        The Flight of Birds
        أَلَمْ يَرَوْا إِلَى الطَّيْرِ مُسَخَّرَاتٍ فِي جَوِّ السَّمَاءِ مَا يُمْسِكُهُنَّ إِلَّا اللَّهُ ۗ إِنَّ فِي ذَٰلِكَ لَآيَاتٍ لِقَوْمٍ يُؤْمِنُونَ[Alquran 16:79]
        “Do they not look at the birds, held poised in the midst of (the air and) the sky? Nothing holds them up but (the power of) Allah. Verily in this are Signs for those who believe.”
        Another verse also touches on birds:
        أَوَلَمْ يَرَوْا إِلَى الطَّيْرِ فَوْقَهُمْ صَافَّاتٍ وَيَقْبِضْنَ ۚ مَا يُمْسِكُهُنَّ إِلَّا الرَّحْمَٰنُ ۚ إِنَّهُ بِكُلِّ شَيْءٍ بَصِيرٌ[Alquran 67:19]
        “Do they not observe the birds above them, spreading their wings and folding them in? None can uphold them except (Allah) Most Gracious: truly it is He that watches over all things.”
        The Arabic word a msaka li terally means, ‘to put one’s hand on, seize, hold, hold someone back,’ which expresses the idea that Allah  holds  the bird up in His power. These verses stress the extremely close dependence of the birds’ behaviour on Divine law. Modern scientific data has shown the degree of perfection attained by certain species of birds with regard to the programming of their movements. It is only the existence of a migratory programme in the genetic code of the birds that can explain the long and complicated journey that very young birds, without any prior experience and without any guide, are able to accom plish. They are also able to return to the departure point on a definite date.
Prof. Hamburger in his book ‘Power and Fragility’ gives the example of ‘mutton-bird’ that lives in the Pacific with i t s journey of over 24,000 km in the shape of figure ‘8’. It makes this journey over a period of 6 months and comes back to its departure point with a maximum delay of one week. The highly com plicated instructions for such a journey have to be contained in the birds’ nervous cells. They are definitely programmed. Therefore, should we not at least reflect on the identity of this ‘Programmer’?
       THE BEE AND ITS SKILL
        وَأَوْحَىٰ رَبُّكَ إِلَى النَّحْلِ أَنِ اتَّخِذِي مِنَ الْجِبَالِ بُيُوتًا وَمِنَ الشَّجَرِ وَمِمَّا يَعْرِشُونَ 0 ثُمَّ كُلِي مِنْ كُلِّ الثَّمَرَاتِ فَاسْلُكِي سُبُلَ رَبِّكِ ذُلُلًا ۚ [Alquran 16:68-69]
        “And thy Lord taught the Bee to build its cells in hills, on trees, and in (men’s) habitations; then to eat of all the produce (of the earth),and find with skill the spacious paths of its Lord.”
        Von-Frisch received the Nobel Prize in 1973 for his research on the behaviour and communication of the bees. The bee, after discovering any new garden or flower, goes back and tells its fellow bees the exact direction and map to get there, which is known as ‘bee dance’. The meanings of this insect’s movements that are intended to transmit information between worker bees have been discovered scientifically using photography and other methods. The Qur’an mentions in the above verses how the bee with its skill, finds the spacious paths of its Lord.
        The gender used for the bee in the above verses is the female gender ( fa’slukî and kulî ), indicating that the bee that leaves its home for gathering food is a female bee. In other words the soldier or worker bee is a female bee.
        In fact, in Shakespeare’s play, ‘Henry the Fourth’, some of the characters speak about bees and mention that the bees are soldiers and that they have a king. That is what people thought in Shakespearean t imes. They thought that the worker bees are male bees and they go home and are answerable to a king bee. This, however, is not true. The worker bees are females and they do not report to a king bee but to a queen bee. But it took modern investigations in the last 300 years to discover this.
        SPIDER’S WEB, THE FRAGILE HOME
        مَثَلُ الَّذِينَ اتَّخَذُوا مِنْ دُونِ اللَّهِ أَوْلِيَاءَ كَمَثَلِ الْعَنْكَبُوتِ اتَّخَذَتْ بَيْتًا ۖ وَإِنَّ أَوْهَنَ الْبُيُوتِ لَبَيْتُ الْعَنْكَبُوتِ ۖ لَوْ كَانُوا يَعْلَمُونَ [Alquran 29:41]
        “The parable of those who take protectors other than Allah is that of the Spider, who builds (to itself) a house; but truly the flimsiest of houses is the Spider’s house – if they but knew.”
        Besides giving the physical description of the spider’s web as being very flimsy, delicate and weak, the Qur’an also stresses on the flimsiness of the relationship in the spider’s house, where the female spider many a times kills its mate, the male spider.
        The parable also has reference to the weakness of such relationship of the people who seek protection for this world and for the hereafter from those other than Allah.
        LIFESTYLE AND COMMUNICATION OF ANTS
        وَحُشِرَ لِسُلَيْمَانَ جُنُودُهُ مِنَ الْجِنِّ وَالْإِنْسِ وَالطَّيْرِ فَهُمْ يُوزَعُونَ 0 حَتَّىٰ إِذَا أَتَوْا عَلَىٰ وَادِ النَّمْلِ قَالَتْ نَمْلَةٌ يَا أَيُّهَا النَّمْلُ ادْخُلُوا مَسَاكِنَكُمْ لَا يَحْطِمَنَّكُمْ سُلَيْمَانُ وَجُنُودُهُ وَهُمْ لَا يَشْعُرُونَ [Alquran 27:18]
        “And before Solomon were marshalled his hosts – of Jinns and men and birds, and they were all kept in order and ranks. “At length, when they came   to a (lowly) valley of ants, one of the ants said : ‘O ye ants, get into your habitations,lest Solomon and his hosts crush you (under foot) without knowing it.’”
        In the past, some people would have probably mocked at the Qur’an, taking it to be a book of fairy tales  in	which	ants	talk	to  each  other	and communicate sophisticated messages. In recent times however, research has shown us several facts about the lifestyle of ants, which were not known earlier to humankind. Research has shown that the animals or insects whose lifestyle is closest in resemblance to the lifestyle of human beings are the ants. This can be seen from the following findings regarding ants:
        (a)	The ants bury their dead in a manner similar to the humans.
        (b)	They have a sophisticated system of division of labour, whereby they have managers, supervisors, foremen, workers, etc.
        (c)	Once in a while they meet among themselves to have a ‘chat’.
        (d)	They have an advanced method of communication among themselves.
        (e)	They hold regular ‘markets’ where they exchange goods.
        (f)	They store grain for long periods in winter and if the grain begins to bud, they cut the roots, as if they understand that if they leave it to grow, it will rot. If the grain stored by them gets wet due to rains, they take it out into the sunlight to dry, and once dry, they take it back inside as though they know that humidity will cause development of root systems which will cause the grain to rot.

    </string>
    <string name="medicine">Medicine</string>
    <string name="med_detail">HONEY HEALING FOR HUMANKIND
The bee assimilates juices of various kinds of flowers and fruit and forms honey within its body, which it stores in its cells of wax. Only a couple of centuries ago humans came to know that honey comes from the belly of the bee. But this fact was mentioned in the Quran 1,400 years ago in the following verse:
         يَخْرُجُ مِنْ بُطُونِهَا شَرَابٌ مُخْتَلِفٌ أَلْوَانُهُ فِيهِ شِفَاءٌ لِلنَّاسِ ۗ [Alquran 16:69]
        “There issues from within their bodies a drink of varying colours, wherein is healing for men.”
        We are only now aware that honey has healing properties and is also a mild antiseptic. The Russians would use honey to cover their wounds in World War II. The wound would retain moisture and would leave very little scar tissue. Due to the density of honey, no fungus or bacteria could grow in the wound.
Dramatic improvements were visible in 22 incurable chest and Alzheimer\'s disease patients at nursing Homes in England who were treated by Sister Carole, a nun, with propolis, a substance which bees produce to seal hives against bacteria.
        A person suffering from an allergy of a particular plant may be given honey from that plant so that  the person develops resistance to that allergy. Honey is also rich in fructose and vitamin K.
The knowledge contained in the Quran regarding honey, its origin and properties, was discovered centuries after its revelation.
</string>
    <string name="psikolog">Physiology</string>
    <string name="psi_detail">BLOOD CIRCULATION AND MILK
The Qur’an was revealed 600 years before the Muslim	scientist	Ibn	Nafees	described	the circulation of the blood and 1,000 years before William Harwey brought this understanding to the Western world. Roughly thirteen centuries before it was known what happens in the intestines to ensure that organs are nourished by the process of digestive absorption, a verse in the Qur’an described the source of the con stituents of milk, in conformity with these notions.
To understand the Qur’anic verse concerning the above concepts, i t is important to know  that chemical reactions occur in the intestines and that, from there, substances extracted from food pass into the blood stream via a complex system; sometimes by way of the liver, depending on their chemical nature. The blood transports them  to all the organs of the body, among which are the milk-producing mammary glands.
In simple terms, certain substances from the contents of the intestines enter into the vessels of the intestinal wall itself, and these substances are transported by the blood stream to the various organs.
This physiological concept must be fully appreciated if we wish to understand the following verses of the Qur’an:
        وَإِنَّ لَكُمْ فِي الْأَنْعَامِ لَعِبْرَةً ۖ نُسْقِيكُمْ مِمَّا فِي بُطُونِهِ مِنْ بَيْنِ فَرْثٍ وَدَمٍ لَبَنًا خَالِصًا سَائِغًا لِلشَّارِبِينَ[16:66 Alquran]
        “And verily in cattle there is a lesson for you. We give you to drink of what is inside their bodies, coming from a conjunction between the contents of the intestine and the blood, a milk pure and pleasant for those who drink it.”
        وَإِنَّ لَكُمْ فِي الْأَنْعَامِ لَعِبْرَةً ۖ نُسْقِيكُمْ مِمَّا فِي بُطُونِهَا وَلَكُمْ فِيهَا مَنَافِعُ كَثِيرَةٌ وَمِنْهَا تَأْكُلُونَ[Alquran 23:21]
        “And in cattle (too) ye have an instructive example: from within their bodies We produce (milk) for you to drink; there are, in them, (besides), numerous (other) benefits for you; and of their (meat) ye eat.”
        The 1400 year old Qur’anic  description of the production of milk in cattle is strikingly similar to what modern physiology has discovered in recent times
</string>
    <string name="Embrio">Embryology</string>
    <string name="embrio_detail">MUSLIMS SEEK ANSWERS
        A group of Muslim Scholars, under the direction of an eminent Yemani Scholar, Sheikh Abdul Majid Azzindani,	collected	information	concerning embryology and other sciences in the Quran and undisputed Hadith 2 and translated it into English. They then followed the Quranic advice:
        فَاسْأَلُوا أَهْلَ الذِّكْرِ إِنْ كُنْتُمْ لَا تَعْلَمُونَ[Alquran 16:43]
        “If ye realise this not, ask of those who possess the Message.”
        All the information from the Quran and the undisputed Hadith concerning embryology so gathered, after being translated into English and presented to Prof. (Dr.) Keith Moore, Professor of Embryology and Chairman of the Department of Anatomy at the University of Toronto, in Canada. At present he is one of the highest authorities in the field of Embryology.
He was asked to give his opinion regarding the material presented to him. After carefully examining it, Dr. Moore said that most of the information concerning embryology mentioned in the Quran and the undisputed Hadith is in perfect conformity with modern discoveries in the field of embryology and does not conflict with them in any way. He added that there were a few verses however, on whose scientific accuracy he could not comment. He could not say whether the statements were true or false, since he was himself unaware of the information contained therein. There was also no mention of this information in modern writings and studies on embryology.
        One such verse is:
        اقْرَأْ بِاسْمِ رَبِّكَ الَّذِي خَلَقَ 0 خَلَقَ الْإِنْسَانَ مِنْ عَلَقٍ [Alquran 96:1-2]
        The Arabic word alaq, besides meaning a congealed clot of blood, also means something that clings, a leech-like substance.
Dr. Keith Moore had no knowledge whether an embryo in the initial stages appears like a leech. To check this out he studied the initial stage of the embryo under a very powerful microscope and compared what he observed with the diagram of a leech.	He	was	astonished	at	the	striking resemblance between the two!
In the same manner, he acquired more information on embryology, that was hitherto not known to him, from the Quran.
Dr. Keith Moore answered about eighty questions dealing with embryological data mentioned in the Quran and Hadith. Noting that the information contained in the Quran and Hadith was in full agreement with the latest discoveries in the field of embryology, Prof. Moore said, “If I was asked these questions thirty years ago, I would not have been able to answer half of them for lack of scientific information”. 1
In 1981, during the Seventh Medical Conference in Dammam, Saudi Arabia, Dr. Moore said, “I t has been a great pleasure for me to help clarify statements in the Quran  about  human development. I t is clear to me that these statements must have come to Muhammad from God or Allah, because almost all of this knowledge was not discovered until many centuries later. This  proves  to  me that Muhammad must have been a messenger of God or Allah”. 2
Dr. Keith Moore had earlier authored the book, ‘The Developing Human’. After acquiring new knowledge from the Quran, he wrote, in 1982, the 3rd edition of the same book, ‘The Developing
        Human’. The book was the recipient of an award for the best medical book written by a single author. This book has been translated into several major languages of the world and is used as a textbook of embryology in the first year of medical studies.
Dr. Joe Leigh Simpson, Chairman of the Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, at the Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, U.S.A., proclaims: “...these Hadiths, sayings of Muhammad (pbuh), could not have been obtained on the basis of the scientific knowledge that was available at the t ime of the writer (implying in the 7th century). It follows that not only is there no conflict between genetics and religion (implying Islam) but in fact religion (Islam) may guide science by adding revelation to some of the traditional  scientific  approaches . . .	there exist statements in the Quran shown centuries later to be valid which support knowledge in the Quran having been derived from God.”
DROP EMITTED FROM BETWEEN THE BACK BONE AND THE RIBS
        فَلْيَنْظُرِ الْإِنْسَانُ مِمَّ خُلِقَ 0 خُلِقَ مِنْ مَاءٍ دَافِقٍ 0 يَّخۡرُجُ مِنۡۢ بَيۡنِ الصُّلۡبِ وَالتَّرَآٮِٕبِؕ[Alquran 86:5-7]
        Now let man but think from what he is created! He is created from a drop emitted – Proceeding from between the back bone and the ribs.”
        In embryonic stages, the reproductive organs of the male and female, i.e. the testicles and the ovaries, begin their development near the kidney between the spinal column and the eleventh and twelfth ribs. Later they descend; the female gonads (ovaries) stop in the pelvis while the male gonads (testicles) continue their descent before birth to reach the scrotum through the inguinal canal. Even in adulthood after the descent of the reproductive organs, these organs receive their nerve supply and blood supply from the Abdominal Aorta, which is in the area between the backbone (spinal column) and the ribs. The lymphatic drainage and the venous return also go to the same area.
        NUTFAH – MINUTE QUANTITY OF LIQUID
        The Glorious Quran mentions no less than eleven times that  the human being is created from	nutfah , which means a minute quantity of liquid or a trickle of liquid that remains after emptying a cup. This is mentioned in several verses of the Quran including 22:5 and 23:13. 1
Science has confirmed in recent times that only one out of an average of three million sperms is required for fertilising the ovum. This means that only 1/3 millionth part or 0.00003% of the quantity of sperms
that are emitted is required for fertilisation
        SULALAH – QUINTESSENCE OF LIQUID
        ثُمَّ جَعَلَ نَسْلَهُ مِنْ سُلَالَةٍ مِنْ مَاءٍ مَهِينٍ [Alquran 32:8]
        “And made his progeny from a quintessence of the nature of a fluid despised.”
        The Arabic word sulaalah means quintessence or the best part of a whole. We have come to know now that only one single spermatozoon that penetrates the ovum is required for fertilization, out of the several million produced by man. That one spermatozoon out of  several million, is  referred to in  the Quran	as sulaalah . We have also come to know now that only one ovum is fertilized out of the tens of thousand produced by the female. That one ovum out of  tens of thousand is also  refered  to  in  the  Quran  as S ulaalah. This word also means gentle extraction from a fluid. The fluid refers to both male and female germinal fluids containing gametes. Both ovum and sperm are gently extracted from their environments in the process of fertilization.
        NUTFATUN AMSHAAJ – MINGLED LIQUIDS
        إِنَّا خَلَقْنَا الْإِنْسَانَ مِنْ نُطْفَةٍ أَمْشَاجٍ [Alquran 76:2]
        “Verily We created man from a drop of mingled sperm.”
        The Arabic word nutfatin amshaajin means mingled liquids. According to some commentators of the Quran, mingled liquids refers to the male or female agents or liquids. After mixture of male and female gamete, the zygote s till remains nutfah . Mingled liquids can also refer to spermatic fluid that is formed of various secretions that come from various glands.
Therefore, nutfatin amshaaj , i.e. a minute quantity of mingled fluids refers to the male and female gametes (germinal fluids or cells) and part of the surrounding fluids.
SEX DETERMINATION
The sex of a foetus is determined by the nature of the sperm and not of the ovum. The sex of the child, whether female or male, depends on whether the 23rd pair of chromosomes is XX or XY respectively.
Primarily, sex determination occur s at fertilization and depends upon the type of sex chromosome in the sperm that fertilizes an ovum. If i t is an ‘X’ bearing sperm that fertilizes the ovum,  the foetus is a female and if i t is a ‘Y’  bearing sperm  then the foetu s is a male
وَأَنَّهُ خَلَقَ الزَّوْجَيْنِ الذَّكَرَ وَالْأُنْثَىٰ 0 مِنْ نُطْفَةٍ إِذَا تُمْنَىٰ [Alquran 53:45-46]
        The Arabic word nutfah means a minute quantity of liquid and tumnaa means ejaculated or planted. Therefore  nutfah	specifically refers to sperm because it is ejaculated. The Quran says:
        أَلَمْ يَكُ نُطْفَةً مِنْ مَنِيٍّ يُمْنَىٰ 0 ثُمَّ كَانَ عَلَقَةً فَخَلَقَ فَسَوَّىٰ 0 فَجَعَلَ مِنْهُ الزَّوْجَيْنِ الذَّكَرَ وَالْأُنْثَىٰ [Alquran 75:37-39]
        “Was he not a drop of sperm emitted (in lowly form)? “Then did he become a clinging clot; then did (Allah) make and fashion (him) in due proportion. “And of him He made two sexes, male and female.”
        Here again i t is mentioned that a small quantity (drop) of sperm (indicated by the word nutfatan min maniyyin ) which comes from the man is responsible for the sex of the foetu s.
Mothers-in-law in the Indian subcontinent, usually prefer having male grandchildren and often blame their daughters-in-law if the child is not a boy. If only they knew that the determining factor is the nature of the male sperm and not  the female ovum! If they were to blame anybody, they should rather blame their sons, not their daughters-in-law, since both the Quran and Science hold that it is the male fluid that is responsible for the sex of the child!
FOETUS PROTECTED BY THREE VEILS OF DARKNESS
        يَخْلُقُكُمْ فِي بُطُونِ أُمَّهَاتِكُمْ خَلْقًا مِنْ بَعْدِ خَلْقٍ فِي ظُلُمَاتٍ ثَلَاثٍ ۚ[Alquran 39::6]
        “He makes you, in the wombs of your mothers, in stages, one after another, in three veils of darkness.”
        Accor ding to Prof. Keith Moore, these three veils of darkness in the Quran refer to:
(i)	anterior abdominal wall of the mother
(ii)	the uterine wall
(iii)	the amnio-chorionic membrane.

EMBRYOLOGICAL STAGES
        وَلَقَدْ خَلَقْنَا الْإِنْسَانَ مِنْ سُلَالَةٍ مِنْ طِينٍ 0 ثُمَّ جَعَلْنَاهُ نُطْفَةً فِي قَرَارٍ مَكِينٍ 0 ثُمَّ خَلَقْنَا النُّطْفَةَ عَلَقَةً فَخَلَقْنَا الْعَلَقَةَ مُضْغَةً فَخَلَقْنَا الْمُضْغَةَ عِظَامًا فَكَسَوْنَا الْعِظَامَ لَحْمًا ثُمَّ أَنْشَأْنَاهُ خَلْقًا آخَرَ ۚ فَتَبَارَكَ اللَّهُ أَحْسَنُ الْخَالِقِينَ [Alquran 23:12-14]
        “Man We did create from a quintessence (of clay); then We placed him as (a drop of) sperm in a place of rest, firmly fixed; then We made the sperm into a clot of congealed blood; then of that clot We made a (foetus) lump; then We made out of that lump bones and clothed the bones with flesh; then We developed out of it another creature. so blessed be Allah, the Best to create!”
        In this verse Allah  states  that  man  is created from a small quantity of liquid which is placed in a place of rest, firmly fixed (well established or lodged) for which the Arabic word qaraarin m akeen is used. The uterus is well protected from the posterior by the spinal column supported firmly by the back muscles. The embryo is further protected by the amniotic sac containing the amniotic fluid. Thus the foetu s has a well protected dwelling place.
This small quantity of fluid is made into alaqah , meaning something which clings.  I t  also  means a leech-like substance. Both descriptions are scientifically acceptable as in the very early stages the foetus clings to the wall and also appears to resemble the leech in shape. I t also behaves like a leech (blood sucker) and acquires its blood supply from the mother through the placenta.
The third meaning of the word alaqah is a blood clot. During this alaqah stage, which spans the third and fourth week of pregnancy, the blood clots within closed vessels. Hence the embryo acquires the appearance of a blood clot in addition to

acquiring the appearance of a leech. Compare the readily available Qur\' anic knowledge with Man\'s struggle with scientific findings:
In 1677,  Hamm  and  Leeuwenhoek  were   the first scientists to observe human sperm cells (spermatozoa) through a microscope. They thought that a sperm cell contained a miniature human being which grew in the uterus to form a newborn. This was known as the perforation theory. When scientists discovered that the ovum was bigger than the sperm, it was thought by scientists like De Graf and others that the foetus existed in a miniature form in the ovum. Later, in the 18 th century, Maupertuis propagated the theory of biparental inheritance.
The alaqah is transformed into m udghah which means ‘something that is chewed (having teeth marks)’ and also something that is tacky and small which can be put in the mouth like gum. Both these explanations are scientifically correct. Prof. Keith Moore took a piece of plaster seal and made it into the size and shape of the early stage of foetus and chewed i t between the teeth to make i t into a mudghah . He compared this with the photographs of the early stage of foetus. The teeth marks resembled the ‘somites’ which is the early formation of the spinal column.
This m udghah is transformed into bones ( izâm ). The bones are clothed with intact flesh or muscles (lahm ). Then Allah makes it into another creature.

Prof. Marshall Johnson who is one of the leading scientists in the USA, and is the head of the Department of Anatomy and Director of the Daniel Institute at the Thomas J efferson University in Philadelphia in the USA, was ask ed to comment on the verses of the Quran dealing with embryology. At first he said that the verses of the Quran describing the embryological stages cannot be a coincidence. It was probable that Muhammad (pbuh) had a powerful microscope. On being reminded that the Quran was revealed 1400 years ago, and microscopes were invented many centuries after the time of Prophet Muhammad (pbuh), Prof. Johnson laughed and admitted that the first microscope invented could not magnify more than 10 times and could not show a clear picture.
Later he said: “I see nothing here in conflict with the concept that Divine intervention was involved when Muhammad (pbuh) recited the Quran.”
According to Dr. Keith Moore, the modern classification of embryonic development stages which is adopted throughout the world, is not easily comprehensible, since it identifies stages on a numerical basis i.e. stage 1, stage 2, etc. On the other hand, the divisions revealed in the Quran are based on distinct and easily identifiable forms or shapes, which the embryo passes through. These are	based		on		different	phases	of	pre-natal
development
        and provide elegant scientific descriptions that are com prehensible and practical.
Embryological stages of human development have also been described in the following verses:
        أَلَمْ يَكُ نُطْفَةً مِنْ مَنِيٍّ يُمْنَىٰ 0 ثُمَّ كَانَ عَلَقَةً فَخَلَقَ فَسَوَّىٰ 0 فَجَعَلَ مِنْهُ الزَّوْجَيْنِ الذَّكَرَ وَالْأُنْثَىٰ [Alquran 74:37-39]
        “Was he not a drop	  of sperm emitted (in lowly form)? Then did he become a clinging clot; then did (Allah) make and fashion (him) in due proportion. and of him He made two sexes, male and female.”
        الَّذِي خَلَقَكَ فَسَوَّاكَ فَعَدَلَكَ 0 فِي أَيِّ صُورَةٍ مَا شَاءَ رَكَّبَكَ [Alquran 82:7-8]
        “Him Who created thee, fashioned thee in due proportion, and gave thee a just bias; in whatever Form He wills, does He put thee together.”
        EMBRYO PARTLY FORMED AND PARTLY UNFORMED
        At the mudghah stage, if an incision is made in the embryo and the internal organ is dissected, it will be seen that most of them are formed while the remaining are not yet completely formed.
        According to Prof. Johnson, if we describe the embryo as a complete creation, then we are only describing that  part  which  is  already  created. If we describe i t as an incomplete creation, then we are only describing that part which is not yet created. So, is it a complete creation or an incomplete creation? There is no better description of this stage of embryogenesis than the Quranic description, “partly formed and partly unformed”, as in the following verse:
        خَلَقْنَاكُمْ مِنْ تُرَابٍ ثُمَّ مِنْ نُطْفَةٍ ثُمَّ مِنْ عَلَقَةٍ ثُمَّ مِنْ مُضْغَةٍ مُخَلَّقَةٍ وَغَيْرِ مُخَلَّقَةٍ لِنُبَيِّنَ لَكُمْ ۚ [Alquran 22:5]
        Scientifically we know that  at  this  early  stage of development there are some cells which are differentiated and there are some cells that are undifferentiated – some organs are formed and yet others unformed.
        SENSE OF HEARING AND SIGHT
        The first sense to develop in a developing human embryo is hearing. The foetu s can hear sounds after the 24th week. Subsequently, the sense of sight is developed and by the 28th week, the retina becomes sensitive to light.
        The Quran explains it thus:
        وَجَعَلَ لَكُمُ السَّمْعَ وَالْأَبْصَارَ وَالْأَفْئِدَةَ ۚ [Alquran 32:9]
        “And He gave you (the faculties of) hearing and sight and feeling (and understanding).”
        إِنَّا خَلَقْنَا الْإِنْسَانَ مِنْ نُطْفَةٍ أَمْشَاجٍ نَبْتَلِيهِ فَجَعَلْنَاهُ سَمِيعًا بَصِيرًا[Alquran 76:2]
        “Verily We created man from a drop of mingled sperm, in order to try him: so We gave him (the gifts), of Hearing and Sight.”
        وَهُوَ الَّذِي أَنْشَأَ لَكُمُ السَّمْعَ وَالْأَبْصَارَ وَالْأَفْئِدَةَ ۚ قَلِيلًا مَا تَشْكُرُونَ[Alquran 23:78]
        “It is He Who has created for you (the faculties of)hearing, sight, feeling and understanding: little thanks it is ye give!”
        In all these verses the sense of hearing is mentioned before that of sight. Thus the Quranic description matches perfectly with the discoveries in modern embryology.
</string>
    <string name="sains">General Science</string>
    <string name="sains_detail">FINGERPRINTS
        أَيَحْسَبُ الْإِنْسَانُ أَلَّنْ نَجْمَعَ عِظَامَهُ 0 بَلَىٰ قَادِرِينَ عَلَىٰ أَنْ نُسَوِّيَ بَنَانَهُ [Alquran 75:3-4]
        “Does man think that We cannot assemble his bones? Nay, We are able to put together in perfect order the very tips of his fingers.”
        Unbelievers argue regarding resurrection taking place after bones of dead people have disintegrated in the earth and how each individual would be identified on the Day of J udgement. Almighty Allah answers that He can not only assemble our bones but can also reconstruct perfectly our very fingertips.
Why does the Quran, while speaking about determination of the identity of the individual, speak specifically about fingertips?  In 1880, fingerprinting became the scientific method of identification, after research done by Sir Francis Golt. No two persons in the world can ever have exactly the same fingerprint pattern, not even identical twins. That is the reason why police forces worldwide use fingerprints to identify criminals.
Fourteen hundred years ago, who could have known the uniqueness of each human’s fingerprint? Surely it could have been none other than the Creator Himself!

PAIN RECEPTORS IN THE SKIN
I t was thought that the sense of feeling and pain was dependent only on the brain. Recent discoveries however prove that there are pain receptors present in the skin, without which a person would not be able to feel pain.
When a doctor examines a patient suffering from burn injuries, he verifies the degree of burns by a pinprick. If the patient feels pain, the doctor is happy, because i t indicates that the burns are superficial and the pain receptors are intact. On the other hand, if the patient does not feel any pain, it indicates that i t is a deep burn and the pain receptors have been destroyed.
The Quran gives a clear indication of the existence of pain receptors in the following verse:
        إِنَّ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا بِآيَاتِنَا سَوْفَ نُصْلِيهِمْ نَارًا كُلَّمَا نَضِجَتْ جُلُودُهُمْ بَدَّلْنَاهُمْ جُلُودًا غَيْرَهَا لِيَذُوقُوا الْعَذَابَ ۗ إِنَّ اللَّهَ كَانَ عَزِيزًا حَكِيمًا [Alquran 4:56]
        “Those who reject our signs, We shall soon cast into the Fire; as often as their skins are roasted through, We shall change them for fresh skins, that they may taste the Penalty: for Allah is Exalted in Power, Wise.”
        Prof. Tagatat Tejasen, Chairman of the Department of Anatomy at Chiang Mai University in Thailand, has spent a great amount of t ime on research of pain receptors. Initially he could not believe that the Quran mentioned this scientific fact 1,400 years ago. He later verified the translation of this particular Quranic verse. Prof. Tejasen was so impressed by the scientific accuracy of the Quranic verse, that at the 8 th Saudi Medical Conference held in Riyadh on the Scientific Signs of Quran and Sunnah, he proudly proclaimed in public:
    </string>
    <string name="kesimpulan">Conclusion</string>
    <string name="simpul_detail">To attribute the presence of scientific facts in the Quran to coincidence would be against common sense and a true scientific approach.
Indeed the scientific accuracy of the Quranic verses confirm the Qurans open declaration.
        سَنُرِيهِمْ آيَاتِنَا فِي الْآفَاقِ وَفِي أَنْفُسِهِمْ حَتَّىٰ يَتَبَيَّنَ لَهُمْ أَنَّهُ الْحَقُّ ۗ أَوَلَمْ يَكْفِ بِرَبِّكَ أَنَّهُ عَلَىٰ كُلِّ شَيْءٍ شَهِيدٌ [Alquran 41:53]
        “Soon will We show them Our Signs in the (furthest) regions (of the earth), and in their own souls, until it becomes manifest to them that this is the Truth it is not enough that Thy Lord doth witness all things?”
        The Qur’an invites all humans to reflect on the Creation of this universe in the verse:
        إِنَّ فِي خَلْقِ السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضِ وَاخْتِلَافِ اللَّيْلِ وَالنَّهَارِ لَآيَاتٍ لِأُولِي الْأَلْبَابِ [Alquran 3:190]
        “Behold! In the creation of the heavens and the earth, and the alternation of Night and Day – there are indeed Signs for men of understanding .”
        The scientific evidences of the Qur’an clearly prove its Divine origin. No human could have produced a book, fourteen hundred years ago, that would contain such profoun d scientific facts.
The Qur’an, however, is not a book of Science but a book of ‘Signs’. These signs invite Man to realize the purpose of his existence on earth, and to live in harmony with Nature. The Qur’an  is truly a message from Allah, the Creator and Sustainer of the universe. I t contains the same Message of the Oneness of God, that was preached by all prophets, right from Adam, Moses, J esus to Muhammad (peace be upon them).
Several detailed tomes have been written on the subject of Qur’an and modern science and further research in this field is on. Inshallah, this research will help mankind to come closer to the Word of the Almighty. This booklet contains only a few of the scientific facts present in the Qur’an. I cannot claim to have done full justice to the subject.
Prof. Tejasen accepted Islam on the strength of just one scientific ‘sign’ mentioned in the Qu’ran. Some people may require ten signs while some may require hundred signs to be convinced about the Divine origin of the Qur’an. Some would be unwilling to accept the Truth even after being shown a thousand signs. The Qur’an condemns such a closed mentality in the verse:
        صُمٌّۢ بُكْمٌ عُمْىٌ فَهُمْ لَا يَرْجِعُونَ [ALquran 2:18]
        The Qur’an contains a complete code of life for the individual and society. Alhamdulillah (Praise be to Allah), the Qur’anic way of life is far superior to the ‘isms’ that modern man has invented out of sheer ignorance. Who can give better guidance than the Creator Himself?
I pray that this humble effort is  accepted by Allah, to whom I pray for mercy and guidance (Aameen).




</string>
</resources>
